In this lesson we are going to be comparing two powerful tools for the finding structure
in TypeScript, which is interfaces and abstract classes.
Move help us enforce consistency across multiple types, but they also serve different purposes.
Let's break down how they work, when to use them and how they complement each other.
First of all, what is an interface? An interface defines a contract. It describes the shape
of an object or a class, but it doesn't actually provide any implementation itself.
So let's do a quick example. So we can do interface. Let's have an interface of shape.
So the shape can define, for example, some methods, so we could do get area, and we could
just say it returns the method returns the number, and we could also have some properties
as well. So we could have shape, for example, sides, and we could have defined it as number.
But any class that implements this particular interface, shape, must define the get area
method, as well as providing the number at all the sides.
Now an abstract class is basically a partially implemented blueprint can include both abstract
methods, I know implementation, and also concrete methods with logic.
So let's look at the difference between it. So we can have abstract, and say abstract
class shape. So notice we have to use the word class here as well as abstract. And now
we can say abstract, get area. So just like before, we are just defining a shape of
a method, but not actually giving any implementation details, but we can also, in a abstract
class, we could have some methods which do have an implementation, so we could say describe,
and that returns a string, and we can say, for example, return this is a shape. So that
means that this actually has a method, which is got some implementation. And for example,
what we are doing things like in .NET, we have something called two string, and we could
have a method like two string on the method. And that's pretty much sets in all the
base classes with the implementation, but that's pretty much the only methods that's
been defined on that class in an object in say .NET. Now we can't actually create an
instance of an abstract class directly, it must always be extended. So that's a difference
between that and the interface. So the interface we actually have to get a class to implement
the interface, and for the abstract class, we can't actually create an instance of the
abstract class directly, we must extend it. Let's learn how to extend this guy. So we're
going to have a class here to class square, and this extends this abstract class shape.
I'm going to have a constructor, and we can say public side number, actually use the
super keyword to be able to call the constructor on the abstract class, which actually
in this case doesn't actually have one, but if we did super, we're then going to call
the constructor on here. So we could of course have a constructor to find on our shape class
if you wanted to. And then we actually need to do override the get area method, and that's
what's TypeScript is complaining about, to come in here and do get area. It needs to have
the same return type, then begin to say return this side, multiply by two, or squared
by two. So abstract classes are ideal when we want to share logic and enforce structure.
Let's quickly undo this and go back to where we have our interface. And for this, we can
actually show you how we can actually create a class that implements this interface. We can
do this in the same sort of ways. So we could say class circle, this implements interface
shape. And now we can define a construct on it. So we could say a public radius, which
is a number. We're going to have an empty implementation for this. And now we can override
the method get area, which returns a number. And for the implementation, we just do return
math at dot pi times this radius squared of two. So interfaces are great for enforcing
structure across unrelated classes. Let's talk about the different key differences between
an interface and abstract class. So for an interface, it can't contain an implementation,
but an abstract class can contain implementation. Now, on an interface, it can't be extended,
but an abstract class can be extended. And both of the classes can be implemented by
a class. What about multiple inheritance? Well, multiple inheritance can happen with an interface
via the implements keyword, but the abstract class can only have one base class. So interfaces
define contracts, whereas abstract classes define reusable blueprints. So we've learned
how to implement interfaces, extends abstract classes and choose the right tool for the
job.